So we are looking at right looking at multi-armed
band it problems, we looked at a couple of
ways of solving it so essentially you try
to keep an estimate of the value function
around, right the value function is the expected
payoff that you get for pulling in all, right
you keep an estimate of the value function
around and then you be have some expletive
fashion with respect to that value function
that you have right.
.
So either you do epsilon greedy or you do
soft max or something and, you get some kind
of asymptotic guarantees correct, yes okay
good, we also spoke about other forms of optimality
so one of them we spoke about was regret optimality
so regret optimality is what, reducing the
total I mean or increasing the total reward
that you get over the process of learning
right, so the initial loss that you get due,
to the exploration you want to minimize.
So that I come as close as possible to the
optimal case as quickly as possible right
so that is essentially what regret is all
about and, so we will start by looking at
one algorithm which in some sense has become
the popular most popular bandit algorithm
around right now, because it's so easy to
implement and also gives you not too bad the
great bounds okay is called the upper confidence
bond, the upper confidence bound algorithm
or the UCB algorithm, okay.
So I will use slightly different notation
today, right not not too different I will
try to as much as possible I will try to translation
the fly, okay to the notation that issued
in the textbook right so even though I will
give we will be giving you some papers to
read, we can take care of linking the UCB
paper and the median elimination paper and
other things right, on what will be giving
you some papers to read and the notation in
the papers will be very different okay.
You probably have to spend like half an hour
just trying to understand the notation, but
when I am explaining it in class to the extent
possible I will try to map it to the notation
is used in the book rights, so that you have
one uniform set of things that you can keep
track of throughout right, the changes or
the following right, I am going to assume
that there are capital K arms right, earlier
I was assuming there were n arms but the terms
of the reason I want to change n is we are
going to now talk about a notion of time right.
So now so they are going to be pull set every
time instant and so on so forth and this should
be familiar to electrical engineer, so if
time is discrete you denote it by n if time
is continuously noted by T right so I want
to be able to denote discrete time, so I want
to use n for discrete time okay and so we
will save n for discrete time and I will not
use it for the number of arms, so that is
the reason I switch to K okay, assume there
are K arms and so as before with each arm
that is associated some arbitrary probability
distributions.
I don’t know that whenever I pull an arm
I will get a sample drawn from that probability
distribution it could be where only it could
be Gaussian right it could be poised on we
do not know what distribution it is but according
to that distribution we will get a, payoff
right and what else do we did we assume last
time there is the expectation given for that
distribution right now yeah we assume that
the distribution is stationary.
It is not going to change the time right and
that there is an expectation associated with
that distribution which will denote by Q*
of A right, when you say Q* of A it is the
expectation for pulling arum A ok.
Let's clear here is a UCB algorithm so there
is assume there are K arms so the initialization
phase is play each arm at least once let play
each arms once right, you have to pull every
arm at least one time you cannot do better
than that agree it, I never pull the arm I
do not know anything about the arms.
So I need to pull each I’m at least one
so that is the least so we start off with
that and then we do the following in a loop,
remember what QJ is estimated payoff as expected
payoff right so this is average reward that
we'll be maintaining right there is a value
function right for arm J so QJ is the estimate
that I have a time n right QJ estimate I have
a time n for arm J.
So essentially what I am doing is I am taking
whatever is the current estimate right, and
I am adding this expression to that right,
and then I am playing the arm that gives me
the highest value for this total expression
right, so the way to think about this is following
I will come back to this it will show things
more precisely later, but let us assume that
this is my, Q of arm one right whatever is
some scale this the x-axis, mean the x-axis
let us assume is armed index and the y-axis
is the expected payoff right.
So that is Q1 then I have Q2 say Q3 and Q4,
let us say I have four arms right so what
the idea behind upper confidence bound is
to say that hey, I am not going to use just
the estimated expectations so far right, so
I've actually drawn many samples right I can
use the samples that I have drawn so far to
figure out, what is the confidence with which,
I can say that this is the expectation right.
.
So you can come you can think of giving some
kind of a bound around this you can say that
ok, this is the expectation I have right but
the true value of Q1 or Q*1 right the true
value of Q*1 is going to lie within that band
right, so intuitively you can see that the
more number of times have sampled arm one
the smaller is this going to be, right if
I have taken a lot of samples then I'm more
confident about the expectation that I am
giving you tell you right we know that as
the number of samples tends to infinity this
QQ will converge to Q*.
So we know that that Q1 will converge to Q*1
if number of times have sampled one goes to
infinity, so the more the number of samples
I draw the narrower will be this band of uncertainty
right, so likewise I will have a band like
this for Q2 right I will have a band like
this for Q3, another band like this for Q4,
so what arm do am I suggesting that you take
now, I am saying take arm one that is what
essentially UCB tells you right.
So why do you think this kind of scenario
meta happened I met a chosen arm for a lot
of times because it seems to have a higher
value, so my uncertainty and the value of
arm 4 has come down all lot right, but arm
one I’m not take n of times, arm 3 obviously
I have not taken n of times, but I am really
not inclined to take arm 3 anymore because
given my current state of uncertainty right,
the probability that arm 3 will be higher
than this end right, a minute it is very small
that even though man certainty arm 3 is very
high I am not inclined to take that arm, because
the chance that it will truly be high a chance
that it will truly be high is very small right.
While for arm 1 the chance that it might be
better than arm 4 it fairly decent so this
is interval I am Telling You is some kind
of bound, that says it with very high probability
like the true value of Q 1, like within this
bond, that means that is a chance I did lie
here which case it can be higher than Q4 right,
so I will k take this if I take this a few
more times and let us say after some time,
my estimate moves up like this but my
estimate moves up a little bit but my bounds
also shrink right.
Now I'd my tonight it might not look attractive
compared to Q4, so I will go back to taking
Q4 right, so that is why you can see in this
expression I have the total number, of samples
I have drawn off arm J right, were NJ is the
number of times I have sampled, I am j so
the larger the NJ the smaller this expression
is going to become, ok a larger the number
of samples I draw the smaller this expression
will become, therefore this interval will
keep coming down.
What that yeah that is more like a normalizing
term right it is there in all the expressions
all the values right all the intervals, that
I compute so it is not relatively it is not
going to matter but you will need it to show
some results later, so there is algorithm
itself clear right, so they explain things
here the n is essentially the number of times
I have played arm so for any of NJ a number
of times have played arm J okay.
So you have that pictorial description of
what this algorithm is doing great, so what
is nice about this algorithm it is very simple
algorithm in saw that right is nothing about
it all you need to do is apart from keeping
track of QJ you have to keep track of NJ,
as well which you are anyway doing if you
are doing that incremental update right, if
you remember last class we wrote the incremental
update so the step size was any way related
to NJ.
So the only additional overhead would be if
you have been using constant alpha for your
updates you will have to remember NJ in addition
otherwise it is exactly the same thing like
we did for epsilon greedy, so instead of random
lead deciding which action to take for exploration
you do not do any exploration also the random
color the random number generator also has
gone now that this is a very deterministic
algorithm right.
So what is so great about it yeah, QJ no because
the other term might be a very small term
Q might be a very large then matter, why does
it matter, they like QJ like the expected
payoff scale me something like ah that way
okay, fine fine fine fine fine yeah, so all
of this this this particular form of expression
does assume that the rewards are bounded between
0 and 1 right, so yeah I will come to that
in a minute.
So yeah you are right, so then you can rescale
the rewards if you want to write as long as
all the rewards are positive so you can rescale
them to lie between 0 and 1 but if you have
negative or reverse you'll have to think about
always not do this okay.